Guttov גוט טוב, Guttov, we're now a דף Daf ahead, so today's
דף Daf is קס״ה, Kuf Samech Heh, 165. We pick up at
the bottom of קס״ד עמוד ב׳, Kuf Samech Dalet Amud Bet, and
we're dealing with the second part of the משנה Mishna now that
we got to all these questions about where to
sign your signatures and concerns about erasures and so on.
So we're dealing with just like the dating of a מקושר, Mekushar,
that a מקושר Mekushar was dated with a different dating system that
was basically indicated the year of the king as one year more
than the other dating system, and then that raised questions about turning
something that was מקושר, Mekushar, if the signatures were on the inside,
opening it up and turning it into a פשוט. Pashut. So now
the גמרא Gemara continues like this: ההוא
מקושר. Hahu Mekushar. It's about 15 lines from the bottom, there's a
little ג Gimmel in a half parenthesis, maybe about 20 lines from
the bottom. ההוא מקושר דאתא לקמיה דרבי. Hahu Mekushar de'ata lekamei deRabbi.
So a גט מקושר Get Mekushar came before רבי. Rabbi. We've seen
before that רבי Rabbi was maybe at a certain time a little
unfamiliar with some of the ways in which a מקושר Mekushar was
done. Okay, and this was actually this thing we saw was quoted
earlier a few days ago. ואמר רבי Ve'amar Rabbi and רבי Rabbi
said, אין זמן בזה. ein zman bazei. We can't say this isn't
a good שטר, Shtar, it's not dated.
אמר ליה רבי שמעון ברבי לרבי. Amar lei Rabbi Shimon berabbi leRabbi.
So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon his son said to him, שמא בין
שרייו מובלע. Shema bein sharav muvla. Maybe the זמן Zman is hidden
between the folds. Which is funny, because the way at least we
perceive of a מקושר, Mekushar, everything is between the folds. But anyway,
it sounds like that wasn't the case, some of the information was
outside, I really don't know.
Anyway, פלייה, Palyei, so he undid the knots, he opened it up.
וחזייה, Vechazyei, and then he saw that there it was, that the
זמן Zman was written inside of the folded-over area. Okay. הדר חזא
ביה רבי בבישות. Hadar chaza be Rabbi bevishut. Afterwards רבי Rabbi was
looking at his son, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, with like giving him
the bad eye, like he was looking at him like angrily or
something.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so it was clear to his son that
his father, as we saw before, his father wasn't so familiar with
some of the aspects of מקושר, Mekushar, which is probably a reflection
of the fact that he didn't like these מקושר Mekushar שטרות, Shtarot,
okay, and he wanted everybody to do פשוט. Pashut. So רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon his son said, hey, like kids always do when they're
accused of something by their parents, is they say, it wasn't me,
it was my brother. So he didn't say his brother, but he
said, לאו אנא כתבתיה, Lav ana kasivte, I didn't write this
שטר מקושר. Shtar Mekushar. יהודה חייטא כתביה. Yehuda Chaita kasvei. יהודה Yehuda
the tailor wrote it, don't blame me. I guess it's a good
position for a tailor to be in to write a מקושר Mekushar
where you're going to have to sew up the fold.
Anyway, אמר ליה כלך מלשון הרע זה. Amar lei klakh milashon hara
zeh. So you know, it's always the coverup is always worse than
the crime. So he said to him, he said, oh, so now
you're telling לשון הרע? Lashon hara? So actually it's interesting that he
considers saying that this guy did a שטר מקושר Shtar Mekushar as
לשון הרע, Lashon hara, but clearly רבי Rabbi was not happy with
it, so he was saying something bad, like at least in רבי's
Rabbi's eyes, about this other person that he did the שטר. Shtar.
You know, we give לשון הרע Lashon hara a very technical sense,
you know, certainly since from the חפץ חיים, Chofetz Chaim, it's like
saying something as opposed to מוציא שם רע, Motzi shem ra, which
is, you know, which is saying a lie about somebody. לשון הרע
Lashon hara is saying something true, but it's something that other people,
you know, that hurts the person's reputation or it's bad in the
eyes of other people. But in the גמרא Gemara also, I mean
which fits in this case anyway, but in the גמרא Gemara you
know לשון הרע Lashon hara also has a very just broader meaning.
It means any bad speech, you know, any speech that you, you
know, could be bad in multiple different ways. But anyway, but here
it certainly fits the narrower technical explanation. Okay. זמנין הוה יתיב קמיה
Zimnin hava yasiv kamei וקא פסיק סידרא בספר תהילים. veka pasek sidra
besefer Tehillim.
So then there was, there were times, or a time, a time
where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was sitting in front of רבי Rabbi
and he was learning תהילים. Tehillim.
Now the phrase וקא פסיק סידרא בספר תהילים, veka pasek sidra besefer
Tehillim, you know, like sort of interrupting his section in ספר תהילים.
Sefer Tehillim. So רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says that means that he
finished one of the sections. ספר תהילים Sefer Tehillim is you know
divided into five books. So he completed one of the books of
ספר תהילים. Sefer Tehillim. אמר רבי כמה מיושר כתב זה. Amar Rabbi
kama miyushar ksav zeh. And רבי Rabbi was looking at the, he
was clearly learning from a קלף, Klaf, right, that's what they had
those days, it was basically oral law and the stuff that was
written was like תנ״ך, Tanakh, and they didn't have, I don't know
when they had codexes, Charlie, when did they start with codexes?
It was around there but Jews didn't use them, it was more
a Christian thing.
Okay. So well, this wasn't yet the age of Christianity, well, I
guess, רבי, Rabbi, anyway, fine. Anyway, okay, but they had scrolls, and
anyway, so whatever it was, but it was handwritten scrolls. So רבי
Rabbi was looking at it and saying, ooh, that's like beautiful writing,
you know, look how square the letters is, how straight the letters
is, what beautiful כתב. Ksav. Okay. אמר ליה לאו אנא
כתבתיה. Amar lei lav ana kasivte. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said,
hey, it wasn't me who wrote it, don't give me the credit.
יהודה חייטא כתביה. Yehuda Chaita kasvei. So again this יהודה Yehuda the
tailor, multi-talented man. I mean I guess if he's writing שטרות, Shtarot,
so it's right, so you can
also. write ספרים. sfarim.
Okay so anyway he wrote it. אמר ליה פוק מלשון הרע זה.
Amar lei puk milashon hara zeh. Wow this guy can't can't win.
Go away from this לשון הרע. lashon hara. What's לשון הרע? lashon
hara? So the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא התם איכא לשון הרע. bishlama
hatam ika lashon hara. I get the first case, it's לשון הרע.
lashon hara. רבי Rebbe didn't want people writing a שטר מקושר shtar
mekushar and he was sort of saying that this guy wrote it.
אמר ליה הכא מאי לשון הרע איכא? Amar lei hacha mai lashon
hara ika? What's לשון הרע lashon hara here? So the גמרא Gemara
says משום דרב דימי. mishum de-Rav Dimi. Following the teaching of רב
דימי. Rav Dimi. דתני De-tani we taught a ברייתא brayta רב דימי
אחוה דרב ספרא, Rav Dimi achiyeh de-Rav Safra, רב דימי Rav Dimi
the brother of רב ספרא Rav Safra says לעולם אל יספר אדם
בטובתו של חברו. le'olam al yesaper adam betovato shel chavero.
Don't even talk about somebody's good qualities שמתוך טובתו בא לידי רעתו,
she-mitoch tovato ba lidei ra'ato,
because by talking about the good qualities it leads to talking about
his bad qualities. Now of course, really you can never compliment somebody?
Exactly. So you know the חפץ חיים Chofetz Chaim I have to
review do חזרה chazara on the חפץ חיים, Chofetz Chaim, but you
know he from what I remember he basically says either it means
like don't be overly effusive because then someone says oh give me
a break he's not that great okay let me tell you about
something he did right. So if you're overly effusive you're leading you're
asking for a reaction or say it's in front of somebody that
we know you know is his enemy or thinks poorly of him
and so on. Okay so which could fit this case not that
רבי Rebbe was his enemy but the fact that רבי Rebbe was
already upset about him or heard something bad about him before about
something that clearly רבי Rebbe you know was you know did not
like. So you know and now you're saying something good you could
say well you know maybe I'll try to
balance it out have him realize he's a good guy. But you
know this is an interesting question that certainly seems reasonable but you
could also understand somebody who is so annoyed and you know it
also depends on like when are you telling it to them. If
you're telling them during the period when they're annoyed they're going to
dismiss it and say oh whatever he doesn't mean anything he's such
a רשע rasha he's such a whatever. Anyway but it's a funny
story because it seems like this was at a very different time
so it is funny that like you can't even say something like
that.
You know but there is a line out there which is something
like what is it? It's like
something like I forget what it is three categories of people like
you know the lowest category
I'm mangling the statement but it's something like those category people who
talk about you know other people and then there's the middle category
people who talk about you know things and the highest category people
talk about ideas. So anyway so okay so that's a form of
לשון הרע lashon hara just talking about people. Why are you talking
about other people? You know? All right anyway certainly the rabbinic enterprise
was talking about ideas. Anyway so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay שמתוך טובתו בא לידי
רעתו. she-mitoch tovato ba lidei ra'ato. אמר רב עמרם אמר רב שלש
עבירות אין אדם ניצול מהן בכל יום. Amar Rav Amram amar Rav
shalosh averot ein adam nitzol mehem bechol yom. Now that we're talking
about לשון הרע lashon hara end up the discussion with a little
bit of לשון הרע lashon hara talking about לשון הרע lashon hara
a little bit of לשון הרע lashon hara or talking about לשון
הרע. lashon hara. Anyway oh that's like that Campbell joke you know
the joke says it says like I never repeat לשון הרע lashon
hara so listen very closely. Okay so
אמר רב
שלש עבירות אין אדם ניצול מהן בכל יום. amar Rav shalosh averot
ein adam nitzol mehem bechol yom. Three עבירות averot that nobody is
saved with and any you know on any day. הרהור עבירה, Hirhur
avera, thoughts of sin, which עבירה avera could just mean any thoughts
of sin but often means sexual thoughts.
עיון תפלה, Iyun tefilla, עיון תפלה iyun tefilla which is sort of
like thinking deeply about prayer whatever I'll get back to that. ולשון
הרע. Velashon hara. And לשון הרע. lashon hara. So the גמרא Gemara
says לשון הרע סלקא דעתך? lashon hara salka da'atach? Really? People speak
badly every day? אלא אבק לשון הרע, Ela avak lashon hara, which
is consistent to what we said before. Even if it's not explicitly
trying to say something bad about somebody but even the type of
case we said saying something good that will lead to something bad.
Or saying something that's a little bit bad in passing you know
or you know in those types of so so you know so
or so so those types of things things that like you have
to be very careful with your speech because even if you're not
intending it can have the dust of לשון הרע. lashon hara. Now
what's עיון תפלה? iyun tefilla? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says עיון תפלה
iyun tefilla means that after you pray you're you think oh I
prayed so good I'm sure God is going to answer my prayers
or let's see if God answers my prayers and in a way
you're like testing God or having too much confidence in your תפלה.
tefilla. But תוספות Tosafot says הלואי, halevai, no תוספות Tosafot doesn't say
this but I'm exaggerating a little, that people should you know should
every day it says בכל יום bechol yom every day take their
דאווענען davenen so seriously that they think oh I prayed so good
God is going to answer my prayers. It can't mean that. That's
not something that would happen every day. So תוספות Tosafot says what
it means is the lack of עיון תפלה. iyun tefilla. It's the
opposite. It's the fact that you just דאווען daven things by rote.
And there's a great ירושלמי Yerushalmi line he quotes at the end
of this תוספות Tosafot עיון תפלה. iyun tefilla. So it
says wait a minute look if you take a look at תוספות
Tosafot he says like this he says ונראה לרבי venira l'Rebbi it's
about eight lines from the bottom with a line that starts with
a Vav in parentheses. ונראה לרבי דעיון תפלה שהוא רע שאינם מכוונים
תפלתם, Venira l'Rebbi de-iyun tefilla she-hu ra she-einam mechavnim tefillatam, they don't
have כוונה, kavana, כדאמרינן k'd'amrinan באלו דברים שאדם אוכל פירותיהם. belu devarim
she-adam ochel peroteihem. עיון תפילה. Iyun Tefila. Okay, ומזה u'mizeh right, ומזה,
u'mizeh, it's a good
thing in some way.
Right. ומזה, u'mizeh, but it means the lack of עיון תפילה. Iyun
Tefila. Okay, that's what it means. It means the absence of עיון
תפילה Iyun Tefila is what the problem is. ומזה אין אדם ניצול
בכל יום שאין שום אדם יכול לכוון בתפילתו היטב. u'mizeh ein adam
nitzol b'chol yom she'ein shum adam yachol l'chaven b'tfilaso heiteiv. Nobody's ever
really able to have enough
כוונה. kavana. Okay. והכי אמר בירושלמי אמר רבי מתנה מחזיקנא טיבותא לרישא.
V'hachi amar b'Yerushalmi amar Rabbi Masneh machzikna tivusa l'reisha. I have to
be I have to you know be grateful to my head you
know be grateful for the goodness that my head does for me
דכי מטי למודים כרע מגרמיה d'chi mati l'Modim kara m'garmeh because when
I get to מודים Modim it bows all by itself. Like I
don't even have to be thinking. Okay, my body is on autopilot
you know when I'm דאווענינג. davening. So it's like I had a
רבי Rebbe once who said you know we say in the דאווענינג
davening it says אלו ברכב ואלו בסוסים ואנחנו בשם ה' אלוקינו נזכיר
eilu v'rechev v'eilu v'susim va'anachnu b'shem Hashem Elokeinu nazkir right? I mean
it's from פסוק. pasuk. You know they go by the horses and
chariots you know to go out into war we call out in
the name of God. So he says when they want to go
fast they go to their horses and chariots. When we want to
go fast we just בשם ה' אלוקינו נזכיר b'shem Hashem Elokeinu nazkir
just start דאווענינג davening because we you know you're done with the
whole דאווענינג. davening.
Okay anyway
so what I was trying to say that like it means it's
a lack of lack of כוונה. kavana.
עיון תפילה Iyun Tefila means a lack and that's why it's אינו
ניצול בכל יום. eino nitzol b'chol yom.
He's bemoaning his own lack of כוונה kavana in that statement in
the גמרא. Gemara. That's what it was?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. I mean he's mocking himself. Right, exactly. My body
goes on autopilot you
know. I remember once I was borrowed somebody's car and I was
asking them how to get to like a mall or whatever he
said don't worry you'll get in the car it knows how to
go all by itself.
So I'd say my head knows all by itself where to bow
down. Anyway alright. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב
רוב בגזל ומיעוט בעריות והכל בלשון הרע. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
rov b'gezel u'miut b'arayos v'hacol b'lashon hara. Most people sin with this
גזל gezel which is pretty harsh okay. A small number with sexual
sins and everybody with לשון הרע. lashon hara. So the גמרא Gemara
says בלשון הרע סלקא דעתך אלא אבק לשון הרע. b'lashon hara salka
da'atach ela avak lashon hara. Fine at least people all you know
you wind up saying something about somebody you know so it's true
like every single day oh you know the רבי Rabbi you know
how was come back from שול shul how was the רבי's Rabbi's
sermon how was this anyway that's what everybody loves talking about is
about the רבי. Rabbi. Anyway but you know but talking about other
people you it's very hard to only say good things about people
and to be especially once if you even say good things sometimes
that's a form of לשון הרע lashon hara as well. The רוב
בגזל rov b'gezel is interesting. Look at the רשב"ם. Rashbam. I know
look at the רשב"ם Rashbam רוב בגזל. rov b'gezel. רוב בני אדם
חשודים על הגזל כעין גזל שמורים
היתרא במשא ומתן ולעכב איש מריוח הראוי לו לחברו. Rov b'nei adam
chashudim al hagezel k'ein gezel shemorim heiteira b'masa u'matan v'la'akeiv ish mirevach
hara'uy lo l'chaveiro. You do business you know you you rationalize a
little bit. You know people at work you know they take a
pen from the from the supply cabinet which they're not you know
and they take it home they're not supposed to take. So you
know all these little things even if you're not you might want
to say like אבק גזל avak gezel right? It's not like somebody
consciously sees themselves as a thief but little ways in which we
rationalize those types of things. They actually did a study once where
I think what they did was like at a workplace they put
a like a can of soda like you know in the middle
of a table in a you know like one like a lunch
area whatever.
I think I've seen
a video like that right? Is there? Anyway and like people would
just take it for themselves. You know then they put a dollar
bill in the middle of the table and nobody took it. So
it was like very interesting what are we able to rationalize for
ourselves like taking a dollar bill that belongs to somebody is stealing
taking a bottle of coke it's just a bottle of coke you
know?
It could be worth more than a dollar.
Well that's true but you know you don't you like it's also
a question of like do you as opposed to like operating by
a rule system it's a lot of people operate by like did
does it make them look at themselves differently? Like will I think
of myself as a thief if I took if I take you
know if I just take a pen from the supply cabinet you
don't think of yourself as a thief you know. You stick your
hand in somebody's purse or somebody's you know and take out five
dollars that's that's you know so even though obviously morally it's the
same thing.
Yeah it reminds me of this story of the ישיבה yeshiva where
this ישיבה yeshiva student who kept having his milk getting stolen and
he put גזל אסור gezel assur and it
didn't do anything and then
they put חלב סתם chalav stam and
that's it very good exactly. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay so רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר הכל כמנהג המדינה. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer hacol k'minhag hamedina. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel said about some of these rules about how to
do a שטר מקושר shtar mekushar or a שטר פשוט shtar pashut
you follow whatever the customs is of that country. So the גמרא
Gemara says רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel so the
גמרא Gemara says ותנא קמא לית ליה מנהג המדינה? v'Tanna Kamma leis
lei minhag hamedina? Are you telling me the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
wouldn't go by that like which is interesting because you might say
like yeah you know maybe the רבנן Rabbanim gave certain rules and
those are the rules that have to be followed. So the question
is first of all is it assuming that מנהג המדינה minhag hamedina
here means the Jewish community or is it assuming the larger secular
society I mean you know number one you know if it was
a larger secular society would be an interesting comment on the intersection
of you know דינא דמלכותא דינא dina d'malchusa dina with with הלכה
halacha but probably it also anyway means the מנהג minhag within the
Jewish community and as such you know גמרא Gemara says like by
a lot of דיני ממונות dinei mamonos it should sort of follow
you know be shaped by the norms of the community. Now even
that fascinating that גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes, takes it for granted, that
everybody would agree to that for שטרות shtarot *Shtarot*. Because if it's
like Michael and I are engaging in some business deal and I'm,
I don't know, I'm asking him to be a שומר *Shomer* or
some type of a partnership
or whatever it might be, it's a sale, it's a contract, you
could say, we're committing
to an agreement and that's implicitly shaped by the norms within the
society that we're operating. Whereas what defines something as a legitimate שטר
shtar *Shtar*, it could be Michael and I both agree that something
should be a legitimate שטר shtar *Shtar*, but it's not a legitimate
שטר shtar *Shtar*, right? That goes by some objective system of law
that's going to determine this if it's done this way, it constitutes
a legitimate שטר shtar *Shtar*. So it is interesting that גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* takes it for granted that of course everybody would agree that
the parameters of a שטר מקושר Shtar Mekushar *Shtar Mekushar* or שטר
shtar פשוט pashut. *Shtar Pashut* would be defined by מנהג המדינה *Minhag
HaMedinah*. Okay, so that's its question. So therefore what's the argument about?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so אמר רב אשי Rav Ashi
*Amar Rav Ashi*, so says רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, so רב אשי
*Rav Ashi* is now going to construct something that is not in
the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, a case in which רבן שמעון Shimon. בן
גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* and the חכמים *Chachamim* would disagree about
whether you go by מנהג המדינה *Minhag HaMedinah* and it would not
be about the specifics of how the שטר shtar *Shtar* would be
written. It's more about the choice to write a שטר shtar מקושר
mekushar. *Shtar Mekushar* or a שטר shtar פשוט pashut, *Shtar Pashut*. So
again inserting all of this in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, there's no
evidence that this is what's going on in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*.
So here's what he says. אמר רב אשי *Amar Rav Ashi*, באתרא
דנהיגי פשוט pashut. *Ba'atra De-Nehigi Pashut*, ואמר ליה עביד לי פשוט pashut
*Ve-Amar Lei Avid Li Pashut*, in a place where the standard is
to write a simple שטר shtar. *Shtar* and the guy tells the
סופר *Sofer* write for me a simple שטר shtar? *Shtar*, ואזל עביד
ליה מקושר mekushar, *Ve-Azal Avid Lei Mekushar*, and he went and he
wrote a מקושר mekushar *Mekushar* שטר shtar. *Shtar*, so קפידא *Kfeida*. That
we assume that since it was both that was the practice and
what was the norm and what he was instructed that the בעל
הבית *Balabais* did not approve of this other שטר shtar *Shtar* and
therefore it's invalid because a שטר shtar *Shtar* that's written without the
consent of the party for whom it's actually coming to testify against,
like if I'm borrowing $100 from Michael and I'm to authorize the
writing of the שטר shtar. *Shtar*. And if it's written without my
authorization or against my authority, my authorization, then it's invalid. So in
that case, we clearly assume that since I was saying it should
be done and that was the norm, I was not approving of
a different type of a שטר shtar *Shtar*. Okay, so קפידא *Kfeida*.
But this is the שטר shtar *Shtar* that would actually effectuate something
as opposed to being a record or a transaction? What? But this
is the שטר shtar, *Shtar* that would effectuate something as opposed to
being a record or a transaction?
No, it could be an עדות edut *Edus* but still
what allows witnesses, if witnesses would come to court obviously they don't
need to
authorize. They saw me borrow $100 from you they can come to
court. But what allows them to turn their testimony into a שטר
shtar *Shtar*, if you want you could say because a שטר shtar,
*Shtar* has implications for לקוחות *Lekkuchos* and so on, or if you
want you could say it's because testimony is supposed to be orally
delivered in court. What allows a testimony to be written and have
the status of a שטר shtar, *Shtar*, it only comes through my
authorization.
Yeah, but what we're saying is if they
witness something and I never authorized it, they can't write it down
and turn it into a שטר shtar *Shtar*.
Right, but if I for instance we do a transaction and you
borrow money from me and then I say alright I want it
to be recorded this way and then whoever it is does it
a different way, so if I don't have a שטר shtar *Shtar*
then I don't have liens on you.
Correct.
Correct. But therefore if you're going to lend me money
then it's hurting you because of the absence of the שטר shtar
*Shtar*. The question is who does the presence of the שטר shtar.
*Shtar* hurt? The person whom the existence of the שטר shtar *Shtar*
hurts is the one that has to authorize it being written. So
if you want to lend me money and make sure you have
liens, you better make sure that I hold back that lending of
the money until I've authorized the writing of a שטר shtar
*Shtar*. That's the way it works, okay. It's called דעת המתחייב *Da'as
HaMitchayiv*, you need the intent or the willingness, the authorization of the
person who is being obligated, who is being hurt by the presence
of the שטר Shtar.
*Shtar*. So it means one of the parties it makes no difference
what they want in terms of the kind of the שטר Shtar
*Shtar*.
Right. unless you could imagine a שטר Shtar *Shtar* whose presence could
negatively impact both parties, like if it's a contract or something like
that that both parties are implicated by it. Okay, so
fine, so that would be a קפידא *Kfeida*. נהיגי מקושר mekushar ואמר
ליה עביד לי מקושר mekushar *Nehigi Mekushar Ve-Amar Lei Avid Li Mekushar*,
or the flip, if the standard was a מקושר Mekushar *Mekushar* and
the
authorization instructions were to write a מקושר Mekushar *Mekushar*, ואזל עביד ליה
פשוט pashut *Ve-Azal Avid Lei Pashut* and then when they went ahead
the סופר *Sofer* and they did a פשוט Pashut *Pashut*, קפידא *Kfeida*.
That's קפידא *Kfeida* and the שטר Shtar *Shtar* is invalid. כי פליגי
באתרא דנהיגי בפשוט ובמקושר *Ki Pligi Ba'atra De-Nehigi Bi-Pashut U-Mekushar*, it was
a place where both options were viable options. ואמר ליה עביד לי
פשוט pashut, *Ve-Amar Lei Avid Li Pashut* and he said make me
a פשוט *Pashut* ואזל ועביד ליה מקושר Mekushar *Ve-Azal Avid Lei Mekushar*
and he went and made a מקושר Mekushar *Mekushar*. So he told
him make the easier one, the simpler one and he made the
more complicated one. מן סבר קפידא *Man Savar Kfeida*, so the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* would say that's invalid because we're going
to assume since even though both were options, since he gave you
the easier option or since
he gave whatever he told you, that was the only only one
you were authorized to do and you were not authorized to do
the other one, okay, and therefore it's invalid. ומר סבר no, מראה
מקום הוא לו mar'eh makom hu lo because he gave you the
easier option, what he was basically saying was like I don't need
you to make me a מקושר. mekushar You could just make me
a פשוט. Okay.
The other way around, presumably, if he said to me make a
מקושר, then presumably everybody would be בסדר. beseder. Okay, but here, presumably
because he said the easier option, what you're saying is the guy
was saying it's okay to make me a פשוט, but he wasn't
insisting that it be a פשוט. Okay. So anyway, the גמרא Gemara
uses this to turn into where it sees other places where there's
debates about whether we take the instructions to be דוקא, davka, only
do it this way, or מראה מקום, mar'eh makom, I'm just like
helping you out and making it easier for you. Okay. I think
I said when we learned this once before that that's a debate
that my wife and I always have when she sends me to
do shopping. She thinks it's דוקא davka בסדר beseder and I think
it's מראה מקום. mar'eh makom. I always come back, she's not happy.
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אמר אביי
רבי שמעון בן גמליאל ורבי שמעון ורבי אלעזר כולהו סבירא להו מראה
מקום הוא לו. Amar Abaye Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel v'Rabbi Shimon v'Rabbi
Elazar kulhu sevira lehu mar'eh makom hu lo. So all these three
תנאים Tannaim hold that in certain contexts, not in all contexts as
we just said, but in certain contexts, you interpret instructions as, you
know, sort of pointing guidelines, pointing in a certain direction, but not
insisting that it be that way. Suggested. רבי שמעון בן גמליאל הוא
דאמרן, Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel hu d'amran, רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi
Shimon ben Gamliel what we said. רבי שמעון דתנן, Rabbi Shimon d'tnan,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we taught, רבי שמעון אומר אם הטעתו לשבח
הרי זו מקודשת. Rabbi Shimon omer im hite'ato l'shevach harei zu mekudeshet.
If somebody says to a woman, the גמרא Gemara actually says that
she's saying to a woman's שליח, shaliach, you know, marry me with
this silver דינר dinar and gives her the money and it actually
was a gold דינר, dinar, she is married because he tricked her
but tricked her and it was better than he was promising. Okay,
so there you could say like no, all when I said silver
wasn't I saying I was only marrying you if it was silver
and it wasn't that you were insisting that it be silver to
be married, I was sort of saying like I'm not promising more
than silver. Okay. Now that's a little bit of a different thing,
you know, that's like, you know, is my description accurate or not
as accurate, you know, does it mean minimally or does it mean
exactly? It's a little different than when I give instructions. Okay.
The next example, you know, a million dollars doesn't mean like oh
yeah, like you know, he's a millionaire and he only has like
a dollar to his name.
No, it'd be the opposite. But the גמרא Gemara says that wouldn't
be included. If I say, if I say, you know, my salary
is ten thousand dollars a year and really my salary is ten
million dollars a year, that's not necessarily good because it could be
that the woman's like I don't want to I can't deal with
somebody who has exactly, exactly. So anyway, but here talking just about
what was given as a כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. Anyway, that's not
as parallel of a case. רבי אלעזר דתנן, Rabbi Elazar d'tnan, רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar we taught, האשה שאמרה התקבל לי גיטי ממקום פלוני
וקבלו לה ממקום אחר. ha'isha she'amra hitkabel li giti mimakom ploni v'kiblo
la mimakom acher. That's a good example. The woman says to the
שליח, shaliach, go over to, you know, go over to the barber
store and get my גט get over there, my husband is over
there. And he got the גט get over in the supermarket. Okay.
It's invalid because she said no, get it at the barber store.
רבי אלעזר מכשיר. Rabbi Elazar machshir. So that's a perfect example. That's
exactly, that's probably where it came from, right? מראה מקום. mar'eh makom.
Are you saying over there is the place, you're just saying like
helping out and just where you'll find my husband or are you
saying no, this is where it has to be? מר סבר קפידא,
Mar savar kfeida, you're insisting, ומר סבר מראה מקום הוא לו. u'mar
savar mar'eh makom hu lo. Fine. So that was how the גמרא
Gemara. re-explained that debate in the משנה. Mishnah פשוט שכתב בו עד
אחד. Pashut she-katav bo ed echad. Now we're going to get to
a fascinating discussion of גמרא Gemara about before we decide one of
the things that makes a שטר shtar valid is that it's been
authorized. But basically a שטר shtar is a logical contradiction because עדות
edus. is supposed to be direct testimony in court and a שטר
shtar is written testimony. So the גמרא Gemara is going to deal
with the question of is there such a thing as a שטר
shtar written by an עד אחד? ed echad? Okay, would that count
as a single person's testimony? Or do we assume the same way
if a single person came to court that would have some validity?
Or do we say no, the concept of a שטר shtar. only
exists when it is two witnesses? Anything else is like worthless, it's
not a שטר shtar? at all, okay? So let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. Because the משנה Mishnah said that if you
wrote a מקושר with two witnesses where normally it would have three
or a פשוט with one and obviously normally it would have two,
it's invalid. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, בשלמא מקושר שכתב בו
שני עדים פסול, Bishlama mekushar shekatav bo shenei edim pasul, I get
a מקושר
that you wrote two witnesses is invalid. איצטריך, Itzterich, you need to
tell me that. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'atach amina, I would have
thought הואיל ובעלמא כשר הכא נמי כשר. ho'il u've'alma kasher hacha nami
kasher. Since two witnesses normally are כשר, kasher, here also maybe it
would be כשר kasher even though you didn't do it the normal
way. And it's telling me no, since a מקושר demands three and
anything less than three is fully invalid. קא משמע לן דפסול. Ka
mashma lan d'pasul. אלא פשוט שכתב בו עד אחד פשיטא. Ela pashut
shekatav bo ed echad pshita.
But if it's a פשוט that was only one witness, of course
it's invalid. Since one witness is one witness, since when does one
witness mean anything? Okay, certainly you can't win a court case based
on one witness. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר אביי לא נצרכה,
Amar Abaye lo nitzrecha, no,
it's only needed to tell me for the following
case: דאפילו עד אחד בכתב ועד אחד d'afilu ed echad bikhtav v'ed
echad dollars from me, and then David comes along and says he
saw Charlie borrow a hundred dollars from me, that they don't combine,
okay? So there's no combination of עד אחד בשטר ed echad beshtar
and עד אחד בעל פה. ed echad ba'al peh. So that is
the חידוש. chiddush. Now, does that mean that עד אחד בשטר ed
echad beshtar is worthless? Like normally for example we have a הלכה
halacha that you have to take a שבועה shvuah against an עד
אחד. ed echad. So if somebody produces a שטר shtar that says
Charlie borrowed a hundred dollars from me and it has one עד
ed signed to it, do I have to take a שבועה shvuah
that that's not true? Okay, or תוספות Tosafot asks a question, what
if there's two שטרות shtarot, and each one says that, you know,
on this day at this time Charlie borrowed a hundred dollars from
דוב Dov and one is signed by ראובן Reuven and one is
signed by שמעון. Two separate שטרות, shtarot do those combine? Okay, are
we saying that it's a problem of combining or are we saying
that a שטר shtar... with עד אחד ed echad is worthless? All
right, so that's an interesting question, keep that question in mind, I'll
come back to that, let's keep on reading the גמרא. Gemara Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
What would we say what that one single witness who signed and
they brought him into court with the other witness who's going to
give oral testimony?
Well, the witness signed, he can also testify orally, but if he...
you have two oral witnesses.
Exactly. You don't need to use the שטר. shtar.
Right. Okay, but does that validate the facts that were in the
שטר?
shtar, Yeah, but it's irrespective of the שטר. shtar Now, the issue
also of the שטר shtar is, and maybe this is partly connected
to what you say, if we say the שטר shtar is valid,
there's two questions about the שטר. shtar. Is a שטר בעד אחד
shtar be'ed echad count even as an עד אחד ed echad to
just prove that a something happened, you know, to be a basis
for something that hasn't
happened? Or and we can go even further, we could say does
it have the weight of a שטר shtar, so that it creates
liens? Okay, because there you could say wait wait, maybe it serves
as עד אחד, ed echad, right, but oh the weight of the
שטר shtar that creates liens, that's something that's a more standard document,
two witnesses, a more public document like that you know a more
weighty one, a more that has and so on, maybe that makes
it also more public. So that's not clear. Okay, but
so one minute... right.
Now it sounds like the רשב"ם Rashbam makes it sound that even
אביי Abaye who says they don't combine is only saying that it
doesn't have the weight of a שטר, shtar. but it sounds like
they would still it would still constitute two witnesses had testified to
that fact, okay? So if you take a look at the רשב"ם,
Rashbam, right, if you look at the רשב"ם Rashbam says, אמר
אביי לא נצרכה, Amar Abaye lo nitzrecha, it's like four lines four
lines down, למיסני עד אחד בפשוט פסול אלא היכא דקמסייע ליה עד
אחד בעל פה, דאתיא מתניתין לאשמעינן דלא סמכינן אשטרא לטרוף ממשעבדי. lemishnei
ed echad bepashut pasul ella heicha dekamessaye leh ed echad ba'al peh,
de'asya matnitin le'ashme'inan delo samchinan ashtara litrof mimeshuabadei. It doesn't have the
weight of a שטר shtar to use to create liens. דשני עדים
כתובין בשטר הוא דמשויה ליה קלא, deshnei edim kesuvin beshtar hu demashvei
leh kala, you need two witnesses to create the publicity. ואינו אלא
כמלווה בעל פה וטורפין מבני חורין כדין המלווה את חבירו בעדים בלא
שטר. ve'eino ella kemilveh ba'al peh vetorfin mibnei chorin kedin hamilveh es
chaveiro be'edim belo shtar. וגם הלווה יכול לומר פרעתי vegam haloveh yachol
lomar parati etc.
But the רשב"ם Rashbam makes it clear that it wouldn't have the
weight of a שטר, shtar. but it would still have the weight
of the testimony of an עד אחד, ed echad, which makes an
interesting question, can I come with a שטר בעד אחד shtar be'ed
echad and would you be forced to make a שבועה shvuah against
it? Okay, so for the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the רשב"ם Rashbam sounds like
it
actually has the weight of עדות. edus, You could question that, and
תוספות Tosafot questions that. It could be a שטר בעד אחד shtar
be'ed echad is zero. Normally written testimony is nothing, you need to
testify in front of a court. The תורה Torah was מחדש mechadesh
a concept of a שטר, shtar, and maybe that written testimony could
become a שטר shtar, and could be like could be considered עדות,
edut but maybe only when it's written in the right way. Maybe
with one עד ed it isn't a שטר shtar at all and
therefore it's nothing. Okay, so for the רשב"ם, Rashbam, for אביי, Abaye,
he says they don't combine but it does have the weight of
a testimony of an עד אחד. ed echad. Let's keep on going.
אלא אפילו וכולי ואמימר אכשיר בעד אחד בכתב ועד אחד בעל פה.
Ella afilu vechulu ve'Amemar achshir be'ed echad bichtav ve'ed echad ba'al peh.
אמימר Amemar goes further and אמימר Amemar says they do work, they
do combine. And according to the רשב"ם, Rashbam, not only they combine
to be the weight of two oral testimonies, that was true even
according to אביי, Abaye, according to the רשב"ם, Rashbam, this would even
give it the weight of a שטר shtar. and would even create
liens. Okay. אמר ליה רב אשי לאמימר. Amar leh Rav Ashi le'Amemar.
So רב אשי says to אמימר, Amemar, והא דאביי מאי? veha d'Abaye
mai? So what about what about אביי's Abaye position? אביי Abaye says
they don't combine. אמר ליה לא שמיע לי. Amar leh lo shmiya
li. Yeah, I never heard of that position. כלומר לא סבירא לי,
Kelomar lo svira li, which doesn't mean I never heard of it,
means I don't buy it, I don't accept it, I believe that
they do accept it, okay.
What,
Amemar was a generation later than Abaye?
Yeah. Okay, after so... אלא קשיא מתניתין. Ella kashya matnitin. But wait
a minute, according to אמימר Amemar the משנה Mishnah is difficult. Because
according to אמימר, Amemar, a שטר בעד אחד shtar be'ed echad actually
can become valid together with the testimony. And we said the חידוש
chiddush of the משנה Mishnah. was to say that a שטר בעד
אחד shtar be'ed echad could never become a שטר. shtar And according
to אמימר, Amemar, a שטר shtar. with עד אחד ed echad could
be a שטר shtar, if you had another testimony to back it
up. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מתניתין הכא קמשמע לן. matnitin
hacha kameshamei lan. Our משנה Mishnah is not being doesn't give the
example of a שטר בעד אחד shtar be'ed echad to say that
that's totally
invalid. The משנה's Mishnah giving the example of a שטר בעד אחד
Shtar Be-Ed Echad to not to teach you something about the מקושר
with two
עדים. Eidim. דשנים במקושר כאחד בפשוט. DeShnayim BeMekushar KeEchad BiPashut. Two witnesses
on a מקושר are like one witness on a simple שטר. shtar
מה התם פסול דאורייתא? Ma Hatam Pasul De-Oraita? The same way one
witness on a פשוט שטר shtar if that's all you have, you
don't have it you know reinforced by a testimony בעל פה, Be-Al
Peh, you just have one thing that has no
validity, it's all by itself one עד Ed is completely פסול, Pasul,
certainly let's say you tried to do a גט Get with an
עד אחד, Ed Echad, that would not be a good גט. Get.
אף הכא נמי פסול דאורייתא. Af Hacha Nami Pasul De-Oraita. It's similarly
if you try to do a גט מקושר Get Mekushar with only
two witnesses, it would be פסול דאורייתא. Pasul De-Oraita. Now רשב"ם Rashbam
and תוספות Tosafot say we don't really mean that, okay, two because
מקושר is only like rabbinic requirements doing it this folded way. דאורייתא
De-Oraita two witnesses is good, but it means we're going to treat
it as if it's פסול דאורייתא. Pasul De-Oraita. So if a woman
is divorced with a גט מקושר Get Mekushar and it has two
witnesses,
we're going to look at it as not like דאורייתא De-Oraita she's
divorced or דרבנן De-Rabbanan it's a problem. I mean that's true, but
the attitude we're going to adopt is going to be she's not
divorced at all, okay. So
אף הכא נמי פסול דאורייתא, Af Hacha Nami Pasul De-Oraita, okay. So
now we find so that's how to explain the משנה. Mishnah. Is
the משנה Mishnah telling you something that two witnesses by a מקושר
is really seen as totally not good, or is it telling you
one witness by a normal שטר shtar is totally not good? So
we have this debate, אביי Abaye thinks a one witness שטר shtar.
and one בעל פה Be-Al Peh do not combine, and אמימר Amemar
says that they do combine, okay.
And how do you say that the משנה Mishnah is not talking
about when another person comes in and? No, no.
Nobody is saying that's the case of the משנה. Mishnah. The question
is why did the משנה mishna have to tell you that a
שטר בעד אחד Shtar Be-Ed Echad is פסול? Pasul? Okay, that's obvious.
So אביי Abaye said it's to tell you that it's totally פסול,
Pasul, it's worthless, you can't even use it together with an עד
בעל פה. Ed Be-Al Peh. אמימר Amemar says no, no, no, obviously
it is פסול, Pasul, it's there to tell you that a שטר
shtar מקושר with two עדים Eidim is equally פסול, Pasul, okay. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, so anyway
now we're going to focus not on the משנה but the debate
of אמימר Amemar and אביי Abaye whether שטר בעד אחד Shtar Be-Ed
Echad combines with a testimony בעל פה. Be-Al Peh. תידע Teida says
אמימר Amemar that it does combine. דשלחו מתם חברייא לרבי ירמיה. DeShalchu
Mitam Chavraya LeRabbi Yirmiyah. That
the colleagues sent to רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmiyah, and we're going to
sort of see at the end of this story that this was
after רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah was kicked out of the בית מדרש.
Beit Midrash. I don't know if you remember that going way back
to the beginning of בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, there was a discussion
if a bird is within like fifty אמות Amot of its nest
so you assume it belongs to the owner, and רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmiyah said let's say one leg is within fifty אמות Amot and
the other leg is out over the line of fifty אמות, Amot,
what would be the הלכה? Halacha? And the גמרא Gemara says על
דא אפקוהו לרבי ירמיה מבי מדרשא. Al Da Afkuhu LeRabbi Yirmiyah MiBei
Midrasha. For this type of a quest for this question they kicked
him out of the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah
always wanted to explore the boundary cases, like literally the boundary cases.
What if it's this scenario? And he creates these crazy cases that
never happen, and he wants to explore those boundary issues, so they
kicked him out. And now I think there's an interesting thing because
a lot of these questions are going to be that we're going
to ask are like boundary questions and they're questions about being out
or being in, or combining with groups or being outside of a
group, so I think there's like a whole theme that's going to
go on here, right. So the very thing about the bird with
a little out and a little in and they pushed רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmiyah out for asking that question. So not to ruin it
but the end of the story is that they're going to send
these questions to רבי ירמיה. Rabbi Yirmiyah. He's going to answer them
from outside the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. A lot of the questions
have to do, can you combine this person with this person? Right,
so it's sort of if you think about it he's outside and
they're in. Anyway, and then at the end of the story is
after he gave his response it says they brought him back into
the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. Okay, so it's an interesting like combining
those stories. Anyway let's take a look. So שלחו מתם חברייא לרבי
ירמיה, Shalchu Mitam Chavraya LeRabbi Yirmiyah, the colleagues sent to רבי ירמיה.
Rabbi Yirmiyah. עד אחד בכתב ועד אחד על פה מהו שיצטרפו. Ed
Echad BiChitav VeEd Echad Al Peh Mahu SheYitzatrefu. If you have one
witness in a document and one oral, can they combine or not?
Okay, so אליבא דתנא קמא דרבי יהושע בן קרחה לא תיבעי לך.
Aliba DeTanna Kamma DeRabbi Yehoshua Ben Korcha Lo Tibaei Lach.
Now there's a debate in סנהדרין Sanhedrin between the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma and רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Korcha about the
following. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that two witnesses only combine if
they are testifying to the same event. These two witnesses say that
I saw Charlie borrow a hundred dollars from David. Okay, if now
let's say however one witness says I saw Charlie borrow a hundred
dollars from David on Sunday and the other witness says I saw
him borrow a hundred dollars from David on Monday. So they're not
testifying to the same event, but the effect of their testimony is
the same, he owes David a hundred dollars. Or here's another example,
one says I saw him borrow a hundred dollars from David and
the other says I heard him admit that he owes a hundred
dollars to David. That's easier because that may be referring to the
same event, but they were different things that they're testifying to. Or
you could even be more extreme. One says I saw him borrow
a hundred dollars from David and the other says I saw him
damage a hundred dollars of David's property, right. So the תנא קמא
Tanna Kama says none of those are good, they have to actually
have
testifying on different things, their testimony can combine.
Yes. Correct. Maybe there were two borrows, maybe he really owes you
two hundred, but at least they can prove that he owes you
a hundred because each one is testifying to the fact that he
owes you a hundred.
Okay, right. They are testifying to two different things, it's not that
they're contradicting. Okay, but nevertheless they can combine. That's what רבי יהושע
בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha says. But the תנא קמא Tanna
Kama says they can't combine if they haven't seen the same thing.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so here's what רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah
said back. אליבא דתנא קמא דרבי יהושע בן קרחה, Aliba deTanna Kama
deRabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kama לא
תיבעי לך, lo tiba'i lach, you don't have a question, דאפילו שנים
בכתב ושנים על פה, de'afilu shnayim be-chtav ve-shnayim al peh, even if
both had been written or both had been oral, okay, לא מצטרפי,
lo mitztarfi, they don't combine. Now why not? Who says that the
כתב ktav and the על פה al peh are testifying to different
things? The כתב ktav said I saw him borrow on Monday at
noon a hundred dollars and the על פה al peh says I
saw him borrow a hundred dollars. Why are we assuming that here
it's like the case of testifying to different events? Okay, that's not
clear at all. So תוספות Tosafos discusses it. For now we're going
to like assume that the גמרא Gemara, is sort of saying that
leaving...
I think here's the simple way to explain the גמרא Gemara and
I'll discuss your תוספות Tosafos later. If both of us were at
the event where Charlie borrowed a hundred dollars on that day, why
did we not write a שטר shtar with two עדים? edim? The
normal thing is to write a שטר shtar with two עדים. edim.
So what is the scenario that you only have a שטר דעד
אחד shtar de'ed echad and you have one על פה? al peh?
It must be a scenario that only one guy was there when
it occurred and the other person maybe heard him admit it at
a different time. Okay, so one way is just the גמרא Gemara
is just assuming that the reason you don't have a שטר shtar
with two עדים edim is that they weren't there at the same
time. Okay, so it's assuming that they were different and saw different
things, maybe one saw the event and one heard the event being
admitted, and that's why you have a שטר בכתב shtar be-chtav and
you have עדות בעל פה. edus bal peh. So it's saying according
to רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, of the תנא
קמא Tanna Kama
obviously they wouldn't combine, even if they were both oral or both
in a שטר shtar it wouldn't be good. אלא כי תיבעי לך,
ella ki tiba'i lach, what's your question? אליבא דרבי יהושע בן קרחה.
Aliba deRabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. According to רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha that says two different...
testifying on two different events can combine.
שנים בכתב ושנים
על פה, shnayim be-chtav ve-shnayim al peh, הודי מצטרפי, hudi mitztarfi, so
maybe if they're both oral or both written they combine. אבל אחד
בכתב ואחד על פה לא מצטרפין, aval echad be-chtav ve-echad al peh
lo mitztarfin, but if one is written, one is oral maybe they
can't combine. אודילמא לא שנא, odilma lo shna, or maybe it doesn't
matter. I'm sorry, this is what they're asking him, all this is
what they're asking him. Okay, so they're asking him this question. So
we get that according to the תנא קמא דרבי יהושע בן קרחה
Tanna Kama deRabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha it does not combine. But what
we want to know is according to רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha even if they're testifying about different events and even
though if they were both witness oral or written it would, what
about if one's written and one's oral? So שלחו להו, shalacho lehu,
he sends back to them, אני איני כדאי ששלחתם לי. ani eini
kedai she-shalachtem li. I am not of the, you know,
I don't deserve the fact that you are asking me this question.
So he's being very humble. After he's been kicked out of the
בית מדרש Beis Medrash he's being very humble. אלא כך דעת תלמידכם
נוטה, ella kach da'as talmidchem noteh, this is what your student thinks,
right? saying like I don't know why you're asking me, you know,
you're the authorities, I'm not the authority. So he's obviously humbling himself
because he was outside the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. Here's what your
student thinks is inclined to think: שיצטרפו, she-yitztarfu, that it would combine.
Okay, that one בכתב be-chtav and one בעל פה be-al peh would
combine. So anyway that's a מימרא's meimra proof back to אביי. Abaye.
אביי Abaye how could you say they don't combine? Here he says
that at least according to רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Korcha, even you know, they do combine. So אמר ליה, amar leh,
so אביי Abaye said back, אנן הכי מתנינא לה. anan hachi masnisa
lan. No, no, no, here's the version we have of that story.
It's different than the version you have of that story. Here's the
version we have of that story.
דשלחו ליה חבריה לרבי ירמיה, deshalcho leh chavrayah leRabbi Yirmiyah, the colleagues
sent to רבי ירמיה: Rabbi Yirmiyah: שנים שהעידו אחד בבית דין זה
ואחד בבית דין זה, מהו שיבאו בית דין אצל בית דין ויצטרפו?
shnayim she-he'idu echad be-veis din zeh ve-echad be-veis din zeh ma'u she-yavo
beis din etzel beis din ve-yitztarfu? They did not send him the
question... we all agree that his answer was שיצטרפו, yitztarfu, they combine,
because as I told you that's the whole idea. He was kicked
out, he was asked this question, his answer was these two separate
things come together and combine and then they bring him back to
the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. So we all agree to that shape,
okay? But the issue was not one בכתב be-chtav and one בעל
פה. be-al peh. The issue was the following. Okay, so one witness
testifies in בית דין Beis Din A and one witness testifies in
בית דין Beis Din B, can the בתי דין Batei Din get
together and confer and and essentially combine the two testimonies? Alright? So
שנים שהעידו אחד בבית דין זה ואחד בבית דין זה shnayim she-he'idu
echad be-veis din zeh ve-echad be-veis din zeh, מהו שיבאו בית דין
אצל בית דין ויצטרפו? ma'u she-yavo beis din etzel beis din ve-yitztarfu?
אליבא דתנא קמא דרבי נתן, Aliba deTanna Kama deRabbi Nasan, now there's
another debate that parallels the debate of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
and רבי יהושע בן קרחה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. It's not if
the witnesses saw at separate times, but if the witnesses... testify at
separate times. Okay? So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says they have
to testify together, and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says they can testify
on different at different times, different days. So again, according to the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma דרבי נתן, de-Rabbi Natan, לא תיבעי לך, lo
tiba'i lach, we don't have a question. דאפילו בחד בי דינא de-afilu
be-chad be dina even in one בית דין beis din נמי לא
מצטרפי, nami lo mitztarfei, they even don't combine,
אלא ella if they're different times. כי תיבעי לך אליבא דרבי נתן,
ki tiba'i lach aliba de-Rabbi Natan, according to רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan.
בחד בי דינא הוא דמצטרפי, be-chad be dina hu de-mitztarfi, in one
בית דין beis din they combine, אבל בתרי בי דינא לא מצטרפי,
aval bi-trei be dina lo mitztarfi, but maybe one in one בית
דין, beis din, one in another בית דין, beis din, they you
can't put the testimonies together. או דילמא לא שנא, o dilma lo
shena, maybe it shouldn't matter. שלח להו, shlach lehu, and he sent
back to them, אני איני כדאי שאתם שלחתם לי, ani eini kedai
she-atem shlachtem li, I'm not worthy that you sent me this question.
אלא כך דעת תלמידכם נוטה, ella kach da'at talmidchem nota, here's the
way that my sort of thoughts are inclined to say שיצטרפו, she-yitztrfu,
that they should combine. Okay, so we should be inclined to bring
people together is sort of the subtext here, right? So מר בר
רב אשי אמר הכי שלחו ליה, Mar bar Rav Ashi amar hachi
shlachu leh, here's what they sent him. שנים שהעידו בבית דין זה
וחזרו והעידו בבית דין זה, shnayim she-he'idu be-veit din zeh ve-chazru ve-he'idu
be-veit din zeh, מהו שיבא אחד מכל בית דין ויצטרף. mahu she-yavo
echad mi-kol beit din ve-yitztaref.
Actually, every testimony was given in court fully properly. Two witnesses came
to Court A and gave their testimony, so it was received properly
by the two witnesses at the same time. Then whatever, Court A
was dragging their feet, wasn't dealing with the case, whatever it was,
they came to בית דין beis din B and they gave their
same testimony, and בית דין beis din B accepted it. Can now
the court, you reconstitute a court that has members of A and
members of B and then judge and them deal with the case?
But they didn't all hear the same... they all heard the testimony,
received properly, but they didn't all hear it in this construction of
the court. Okay? אליבא דרבי נתן לא תיבעי לך. aliba de-Rabbi Natan
lo tiba'i lach. So according to רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, that says
that when they testify, witnesses testify in different courts, one in, you
know, or at different times, they combine, that's then it's obvious it
should be good. השתא עדות דלא מצטרפי דייני מיבעיא. hashta edut de-lo
mitztarfi dayani miba'aya. If witnesses can combine even when they're separate times
and normally the idea of a witness is one unit or, you
know, one act of receiving the testimony, if that can be become
one act, so certainly once the testimony's been received properly, the court
can combine. Now, again, I don't exactly get why it's a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. Like what, what rules do we have about reconstituting
a court with different members of different courts? You know, it's not
clear to me why the Gemara takes that that's obvious that that
works.
What? Right, I mean, I think that the point, I think the
Gemara assumes that עדות eidus. we have a concept of like there's
a כת kat and therefore maybe they all have to be one
unit and combined and so on and it should have higher levels
than the idea of a בית דין. beis din. But who knows,
you know? Anyway, that's the Gemara's assumed, okay? כי תיבעי
לך אליבא דתנא קמא דרבי נתן.
ki tiba'i lach aliba de-Tanna Kamma de-Rabbi Natan.
I want to know according to the תנא קמא that says that
עדים edim can't testify at different times. עדים הוא דלא מצטרפי, edim
hu de-lo mitztarfi, witnesses don't, אבל דייני מצטרפי, aval dayani mitztarfi, but
judges, as long as the עדים edim gave it properly in בית
דין beis din A and properly in B, the judges can combine.
או דילמא לא שנא, o dilma lo shena, maybe not. שלח להו,
shlach lehu, and he sent back to them, we all know the
answer. אני איני כדאי שאתם שלחתם לי, ani eini kedai she-atem shlachtem
li, I'm not worthy that you're asking me. אלא כך דעת תלמידכם
נוטה שיצטרפו, ella kach da'at talmidchem nota she-yitztrfu, here's what I'm inclined
to say, that they should combine. רבינא, Ravina, fourth version. רבינא אמר
הכי שלחו ליה. Ravina amar hachi shlachu leh. Here's what they sent
him. שלשה שישבו לקיים את השטר. shlosha she-yashvu le-kayem et ha-shtar. Three
people sat to be מקיים mekayem the שטר. shtar? And you need
a בית דין beis din to do קיום השטר, kiyum ha-shtar, to
validate. ומת אחד מהם, u-met echad me-hem,
and one died. צריכי למכתב במושב תלתא הוינא וחד ליתוהי tzrichi le-michtav
be-moshav tlata havina ve-chad leitei
או
לא? o lo? Do they have to write, in you know, we
were three of us together were here and one, one is no
longer with us, or can they just write the three of us
together sat and were מקיים mekayem the שטר? shtar. Like how much
do they have to be transparent about the fact that one of
them is no longer around, which also obviously, you know, a little
bit evokes, although it's a little more drastic, the רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmiyah situation, right? You know, we are no longer the full בית
מדרש beis medrash that we were, one of us is no longer
here, you know? And almost echoes also by the brothers of יעקב,
Yaakov, right? You know, what is it? האחד איננו, ha-echad einennu, right?
Anyway, one is no longer with us. So how much do we
have to acknowledge that? Yes.
All of this echoes the situation of רבי ירמיהו, Rabbi Yirmiyahu, because
he's no longer here with us.
I know, that's the whole point, I was saying it from the
very beginning, that it's all about bringing somebody together, and now it's
acknowledging that somebody is no longer with us. Okay? או ליתוהי, o
leitei, oh, או לא? o lo? שלח להו, shlachu lehu, he sent
back to them: אני איני כדאי שאתם שלחתם לי, ani eini kedai
she-atem shlachtem li, I'm not worthy that you sent me. אלא כך
דעת תלמידכם נוטה שצריכים למכתב במושב תלתא הוינא וחד ליתוהי. ella kach
da'at talmidchem nota she-tzrichim le-michtav be-moshav tlata havina ve-chad leitei. You have
to write it, you have to acknowledge that one is no longer
here. And the Gemara ends by saying ועל דא עיילוהו לרבי ירמיה
לבי מדרשא. ve-al da ayiluhi le-Rabbi Yirmiyah le-vei midrasha. And because of
this, because maybe of the humility that he showed, but also it
seems like there were coded messages going in both directions, he wanted
to come back, you know, they wanted him back, or something like
that. Anyway, they brought him back to the בית מדרש. beis medrash.
Now I want to say something about the שטר shtar, issue because
from this the שטר... shtar This גמרא, Gemara certainly the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam reads it, it gives a lot of weight to a
שטר בעד אחד. shtar b’eid echad. Number one is according to אמימר
Ameimar they really combined, and it really has the function of a
שטר. shtar And according to even according to אביי, Abaye, according to
the רשב"ם, Rashbam, it maybe doesn’t have the weight of a שטר,
shtar, but it has the weight of a testimony of an עד
אחד, eid echad, and the two combined would have the weight of
עדות. eidus, תוספות Tosafot does not like this. תוספות Tosafot says the
fact that the גמרא Gemara. did not ask, what about one שטר
shtar, with עד אחד eid echad and another שטר shtar with עד
אחד, eid echad, let those
combine? To that תוספות Tosafot is a signal that a normal שטר
בעד אחד shtar b’eid echad might not have any value. So if
it doesn’t have any value, how could it combine with אחד על
פה? echad al peh? So תוספות Tosafot says no, no, no. Here’s
what the אחד על פה echad al peh is doing. He really
radically limits it. What the אחד על פה echad al peh is
doing is one שטר shtar says Charlie borrowed a hundred dollars from
David. David is now the one holding the שטר. shtar And then
I come along, so Eli signed the שטר, shtar and I come
along and I say I saw Charlie hand the שטר shtar, over
to David. So I’m not testifying that Charlie borrowed the hundred dollars.
I’m testifying that he handed over the שטר. shtar? And if anybody
knows anything about גיטין Gittin or whatever, there’s a principle of עדי
מסירה. edei mesirah. עדי edei that see the שטר shtar handed over
somehow are combined to the testimony of the שטר. shtar So for
תוספות, Tosafot, that’s the scenario we’re asking. Because I’m testifying to the
handing over the שטר, that should make it like I’m a co-signer
of the שטר, and like it’s a שטר has two עדים. eidim.
So תוספות Tosafot very much limits it to that scenario. תוספות Tosafot
because תוספות Tosafot’s basic approach is שטר בעד אחד shtar b’eid echad
is worthless. The תורה Torah only was מחדש mechadesh the idea of
שטרות shtarot with two witnesses. So the only question here is by
testifying to the handing over, that makes it like I have co-signed
that שטר. This תוספות Tosafot says that’s why the גמרא Gemara treats
it like we’re testifying to different things, because Eli’s testifying to the
fact that Charlie borrowed the hundred dollars, I’m testifying to the fact
that the שטר was handed over. Why was the גמרא Gemara assuming
that the כתב ksav and the על פה al peh were testifying
to different, remember that was the assumption of the גמרא. Gemara So
according to תוספות, Tosafot, this is why, because they’re actually one is
only about the handing over and one was the signature on the
שטר. Anyway, that’s but that’s one approach of תוספות. Tosafot. This גמרא
Gemara, is really important and interesting. Is there any halachic weight? א,
alef, does it count as a שטר, but ב, beis, does it
even count as עדות, eidus. עד אחד בכתב? eid echad b’ksav? Maybe
the תורה Torah was only מחדש mechadesh the idea of שטרות with
two witnesses. So that’s how תוספות Tosafot wants to set a limit
the case. Then תוספות Tosafot quotes a ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, and if you
look at the last line of תוספות Tosafot on קס"ה עמוד א',
kuf samech hei amud alef, ירושלמי Yerushalmi also does not like the
idea of a שטר בעד אחד, shtar b’eid echad, and the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi has the same question, but the ירושלמי Yerushalmi limited in the
following way. So look at the bottom of תוספות, Tosafot, two lines
from the bottom on קס"ה עמוד א'. kuf samech hei amud alef.
He says ובירושלמי גרסינן, u’v’Yerushalmi garsinan,
and in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi here’s the version we’ve got. בעי ר'
זעירא, ba’ei Rabi Zeira, עד אחד בכתב ועד אחד על פה מהו?
eid echad b’ksav v’eid echad al peh mahu? שיצטרפו? she’yitztarfu? Can you
combine one written with one oral? So the גמרא says ועד אחד
בכתב כלום הוא? v’eid echad b’ksav klum hu? What, has one עד
eid on a שטר worth anything? So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi takes the
same assumption. There’s no such thing as a שטר בעד אחד. shtar
b’eid echad. It has zero value. So how can you ask this
question? So גמרא says לא כך צריכא. lo kach tzericha. No, no,
no, here’s the question. כשהיו שנים ומצאו לקיים כתב ידו
של ראשון ולא מצאו לקיים כתב ידו של שני. k’she’hayu shnayim u’matzu
l’kayeim ksav yado shel rishon v’lo matzu l’kayeim ksav yado shel sheini.
The שטר had two witnesses, but we were only able to validate
one.
So it’s a great case. A שטר with one witness isn’t a
שטר. It’s a worthless piece of paper. It’s somebody’s scratchings. This שטר
has two witnesses, but we can only accept the testimony of one
of them. We only have proof that one was validly signed. So
it’s like an interesting combination. It’s a probably a good שטר or
possibly a good שטר with two witnesses, but at this stage we
only know that one of the witnesses on the שטר is testifying.
So you could say until you know that both are good it’s
not good at all, but it’s not the same that there’s only
one signature on it. All right, so this is a really interesting
question. Does a שטר with one signature worth anything? And the question
is, like the רשב"ם Rashbam says, yeah, like everybody agrees it’s real
עדות. The only question is does it have the weight of a
שטר? Okay, so the
רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot says like, no, if it’s just that,
it’s nothing. Everybody agrees it does not combine and it’s nothing. The
only case we’re talking about is that the other עד eid saw
it being handed over and that should make it like two witnesses
signed the שטר. All right, let’s take a look now at the
next משנה. So it
seems like though like
אביי Abaye because of the extra stories that were brought here...
Oh, that’s an interesting question. That’s just, I don’t know, it’s not
clear how we should rule. The extra stories just say that רבי
ירמיה Rabi Yirmiyah didn’t resolve the question. It’s not exactly clear what’s
for
אמימר... Ameimar... Yeah, so it’s true. I don’t know, it’s a good
question how they פוסקין. paskin. Have to check. Okay, now that we’re...
With that whole thing that led us to these complicated discussions of
מקושר and פשוט, the rest of this פרק perek becomes a lot,
I don't know, easier, or at least more conceptual, and it deals
with questions about like, what's written in the שטר, okay? Or we'll
see, related issues. So, כתבו, kasvu, let's say in the שטר was
written
זוזין מאה דאינון סלעין עשרין. zuzin mea de-innun sela-in esrin. Charlie borrowed
from David a hundred זוז zuz which is twenty סלע. sela. Now
the problem is that a hundred זוז zuz is twenty-five סלע. sela.
So the the amounts in the שטר don't line up, okay? But
they're written as if it was the same amount.
So אין לו
אלא עשרין. ein lo ela esrin. So David can only collect twenty.
The principle is יד בעל השטר על התחתונה. yad ba'al hashtar al
hatachtona. David is
trying to extract money from Charlie based on the testimony of the
שטר, המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechaveiro alav haraya, David has the
burden of proof, so you have to read the שטר, if there
are contradictory languages, you have to read it in its minimalist way,
okay? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says it's also possible it's true because
again, the coins there were of precious metal, so were worth their
weight, so it's possible that like twenty סלע sela is worth a
hundred light
זוז zuz or something like that. So it's possible that if it's
weighty סלעין sela-in and light זוזין, zuzin, it's possible they line up.
But even if they didn't line up,
you're going to go by the minimalist reading. One minute. Now, let's
say it
said זוזין מאה דאינון תלתין סלעין, zuzin mea de-innun tlatin sela-in, a
hundred זוז zuz which is thirty סלע, sela, again, that's not right,
it's twenty-five, אין לו אלא מנה. ein lo ela mane. So you
can only collect a hundred זוז, zuz, you have to do the
minimal of the
two. Okay. כתב זוזין דאינון, kasav zuzin de-innun, now let's say the
שטר said he
borrowed silver זוז zuz to the amount of and nobody filled in
the blank.
In the amount of blank, okay? ונמחק ve-nimchak and the amount is
erased. Of course, if I were David, before I brought the שטר
to בית דין, beis din, if that amount had been erased, I'd
get somebody to fill it in. Of course, the problem is as
we saw before, you could tell something was written on the מחק.
machak. Okay. So you're not going to do that, then people are
going to think that you intentionally forged it and made it up,
but okay, now it's erased. We don't know what. מיגו? migo?
Yeah,
I guess, but what's the lowest possible number? Two, right? So אין
פחות משנים. ein pachos mishnayim. David, the most you can collect is
two. Charlie borrowed dollars in the amount of blank. So minimalist way,
two. Sorry, that's all you're entitled to. כסף סלעין דאינון kesef sela-in
de-innun and now I don't know why we have to say the
rest, it's all the same, סלע, sela, silver סלע, sela, which are
in the amount of blank, ונמחק, ve-nimchak, אין פחות משנים, ein pachos
mishnayim, two. דרכונות דאינון, darkonos de-innun, דרכונות, darkonos, what's that called? דרכונין?
darkonin? What was the Greek...
this was a Roman coin, Charlie?
Gold coin, it says.
Okay. Okay,
דרכונין, darkonin, it makes sense, we move from silver to gold. Anyway,
ונמחק, ve-nimchak, אין פחות משנים. ein pachos mishnayim. What?
He puts two סלעין. sela-in.
Okay. So that's two. Okay, fine. So anyway, you read it in
the minimalist way, whether there's a contradiction, whether the amount is erased,
you're going to give it the minimalist interpretation. כתב בו מלמעלה מנה
ומלמטה מאתים. kasav bo milmala mane umilmata masayim. Let's say there's a
clear contradiction, not in that they seem to be explaining one another,
this equals this. It's literally, at the top of the שטר it
says he borrowed a hundred, and at the bottom of the שטר
it says he borrowed two hundred. Okay, מלמעלה מאתים ומלמטה מנה milmala
masayim umilmata mane or the opposite, הכל הולך אחר התחתון. hakol holeich
achar hatachton. Here we don't go by the minimalist. Here they're clearly
contradictory,
it wasn't there's a conflict,
but they're clearly contradictory, and the principle is the stuff at the
bottom is the more binding part of the document. Now, it's not
the last line. Remember, you don't learn anything from the very last
line. Okay. So then but now the משנה asks,
אם כן למה כותבין את העליון? im kein lama kosevin es ha-elyon?
If the only thing that's going to dictate is the recapping at
the end of the שטר, why do you write the beginning of
the שטר? שאם תמחק אות אחת מן התחתון תלמד מן העליון. she-im
timachek os achas min hatachton tilmad min ha-elyon. Because if the bottom
of the שטר has some erasure, then you can fill in the
blanks based on what the narrative at the top. So you repeat
it in order that there's like a backup copy of it as
it were, so that you can correct any ambiguities. But the binding
part is the part at the end. Okay, let's look at a
little bit of the גמרא, תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. אמר כסף, amar
kesef, if the שטר says Charlie borrowed silver, אין פחות מדינר כסף,
ein pachos middinar kesef, so that means one דינר dinar of silver.
Okay.
כסף דינרין kesef dinarin and דינרי כסף, dinarei kesef, if it says
Charlie borrowed דינרין dinarin of silver or silver דינרין, dinarin, so it
uses the plural, אין פחות משני דינרין כסף, ein pachos mishnei dinarin
kesef, so it means at least, so again, we'll interpret it to
mean two.
כסף בדינרין, kesef bidinarim, Charlie borrowed silver in the amount of דינרין,
dinarin, so אין פחות מבשני דינרים זהב. ain pachos mibishnei dinarim zahav.
So that's interesting because it didn't say silver דינרי, dinarei,
but it said silver in the amount of דינרין, dinarin, so we
assume that the דינרין dinarin refers to a different metal, refers to
gold. Okay, so we assume he borrowed silver silver coins in the
amount of the minimal read of two gold דינרי. dinarei.
Now,
אין פחות מבשני דינרים זהב כסף. ain pachos mibishnei dinarim zahav kesef.
Two דינרי dinarei of gold, he borrowed silver in the amount of
two דינרי dinarei of gold. Okay. אמר מר. amar mar. Now we're
going to unpack this. כסף אין פחות מדינר כסף. kesef ain pachos
midinar kesef. It just says silver, we assume it means a silver
דינר. dinar. ואימא נסכא? veima naska? Maybe it means a silver bar,
how do we know it means a silver coin? Okay. So אמר
רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar דכתיב ביה מטבע. dekasiv bei matbea. It
says he borrowed silver coins or a silver coin or whatever. It's
clear that it's referring to coins, not just to the straight metal.
ואימא פרוטה? veima pruta? So maybe it means not, you know, a
coin smaller than a דינר, dinar, like pennies? Maybe it means like
silver pennies? So אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa באתרא דלא סגיא
בפרוטה דכספא. baasra dlo sagya bipruta dechaspa. No, no, no. People don't
use, פרוטות prutos are נחושת, nechoshes, right? A standard, that's a פרוטה,
pruta, right? It's copper. People don't have silver coins in the size
of pennies. Silver's only דינרי, dinarei, not smaller, or at least in
this place that was not prevalent. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So let's
just read one more.
Same point except with gold. זהב. zahav. If it says he borrowed
gold, אין פחות מדינר זהב. ain pachos midinar zahav. It's one דינר.
dinar. זהב דינרין zahav dinarin ודינרין זהב. vdinarin zahav. If it says
דינרי dinarei of gold, אין פחות משני דינרין זהב. ain pachos mishnei
dinarin zahav. Then it's two. זהב בדינרין, zahav bidinarim, gold in the
amount of
דינרין, dinarin, אין פחות מבשני דינרין כסף זהב. ain pachos mibishnei dinarin
kesef zahav. So this is the flip because you have the word
in דינרי, dinarei, it's you're borrowing gold in the amount of two
דינרי dinarei of silver. Okay, because you use the word בדינרין bidinarin
which somehow indicates that you're doing it with a different type of
metal. Okay. אמר מר. amar mar. So now to begin to unpack
it. זהב אין פחות מדינר זהב. zahav ain pachos midinar zahav. Gold
means one דינר. dinar. ואימא נסכא? veima naska? Maybe it means an
ingot of gold. אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar דכתיב ביה מטבע.
dekasiv bei matbea. No, it's clear we're dealing with coins. ואימא פרוטה?
veima pruta? Maybe it means pennies of gold? Imagine how big a
gold penny would be. דפרוטה דדהבא לא עבדי אינשי. depruta dedahava lo
avdi inshi. Okay, no. People don't make, in the past we said
it was a place they didn't have silver pennies, here we're saying
nobody makes gold pennies. Okay, so it can't be possible. So we're
going to continue tomorrow to figure out the question about why when
it says in דינרי dinarei does it mean in the different, you
know, in the different metal. Okay, so we'll continue with the word,
you know, זהב בדינרין zahav bidinarim or כסף בדינרין kesef bidinarim and
why that means in the different metal, we'll continue with that tomorrow.
Yes, Charlie.
One possibility.